Guide to the Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter Records, 1980 - 2003 UA.31.13.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter records
1980 - 2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alpha Phi Omega. Lambda Nu Chapter (Duke University)
UA.31.13.0002
17.5 Linear Feet
The Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter was founded in 1955 at Duke University. The student service fraternity performs variety of volunteer activities in Durham as well as greater North Carolina and South Carolina. The Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter Records contain minutes, reports, correspondence, administrative information, slides, composite photographs, audio tapes, scrapbooks, and other materials. English.
3500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter Records was received by the University Archives as several transfers in 2004.
Historical Note
The following brief history appears on the Lambda Nu website: http://www.duke.edu/apo/
Lambda Nu Chapter of Alpha Phi Omega was founded at Duke University in 1955 by Thomas R. Neese. Encouraged by area Boy Scout representative Bill Roth, Neese recruited Robert M. Graper and Joseph Griffin, fellow brothers of the Phi Kappa Sigma fraternity. Together, they organized the first pledge class with assistance from Rho Chapter of UNC-Chapel Hill. Sixteen men comprised this initial group, which first met in February of 1955. Potential service projects were discussed at this meeting, and the future Brothers choose a project blazing a nature trail at the Durham Children's Museum (now the Museum of Life and Science). This first project, which preceded the chartering of Lambda Nu, has been a regular project of the Chapter ever since.
The Chapter grew in prestige during the 1960s, despite a membership which hovered around twenty men during most of this period, and a need to establish itself among larger service organizations at Duke. APO appeared successful, expanding its service program to include a diverse range of projects.
In 1974, Lambda Nu began accepting women, a full two years before the National fraternity went co-ed. The Chapter was able to do this by submitting membership lists to the National office that included only first initials and last names. Soon afterwards, however, the Chapter began to drift apart, with its last active member deactivating around 1978.
In the Spring of 1979, Duke sophomore Bob McMahan learned about APO from friends who were Brothers at the Iota Lambda Chapter at North Carolina State. McMahan spent the fall 1979 semester researching the history of Lambda Nu and recruiting interested people. By April of 1980, Lambda Nu was reborn, initiating nineteen pledges.
As Duke grew during the 1980s, so did Lambda Nu. Alpha Phi Omega celebrated the opening of the Bryan Center in 1982 helping the Duke University Union raise money to buy the baby grand piano that now sits in the Center's Schaefer Mall. By the end of the 1980s, the Chapter was annually performing thousands of hours of service for the Durham community, working for groups like the Eno River State Park, Lenox Baker Children's Hospital, Genesis Home, Duke Rescue Mission, and many local hospitals, schools and shelters. In addition, the chapter's fundraising efforts grew to a donation approaching ten thousand dollars each year to a local charity.
Collection Overview
The Alpha Phi Omega, Lambda Nu Chapter Records include minutes, reports, correspondence, administrative information, slides, photographs, audio tapes, scrapbooks, and other materials documenting the history of this service fraternity. The first series, Administrative, contains information about the membership, volunteer work, social activities, and alumni of Lambda Nu. The second series, Slides, contains slides of Lambda Nu activities from 1980 to 1997. The next series, Audio Recordings, has one audio cassette of the 1998 Senior Banquet. The fourth series, Composite Photographs, contains photographs of all Lambda Nu Members during most school years between 1986 and 2002. The Scrapbooks series contains photographs, documents, handwritten notes, and other materials assembled by Lambda Nu members. The final series, Oversize Materials, houses oversize scrapbooks.
Related Material
Fraternities and Sororities Collection
Duke University Archives
Audiocassettes; Scrapbooks; Student service -- North Carolina; Color slides; Composite photographs; Volunteers -- North Carolina; Voluntarism; Alpha Phi Omega. Lambda Nu Chapter (Duke University); Alpha Phi Omega; Alpha Phi Omega. Lambda Nu Chapter (Duke University); Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Duke University -- Societies, etc.
- Administrative, 1985-2001
  Scope and Contents note
  The Administrative series contains materials used by chapter leaders in their administration of Lambda Nu, including minutes, reports, correspondence, slides, and information on volunteer projects, membership, social activities, alumni, and the history of the chapter. Much of the material was originally housed in binders, and the original arrangement of papers has been retained. Folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Administrative Materials, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Administrative Materials, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Alumni Survey and Letters, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Address and Phone Lists, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Materials, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Correspondence, Fall 1990-Spring 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Administrative Materials, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Conferences, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Chapter Record," May 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alpha Phi Omega national History, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Growing Pains: Making the Transition to a Larger Chapter," Fall 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Administrative Materials, Fall 1993-Fall 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Roll Call, Fall 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Conferences, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Josiah Frank Historians Award Application, 1995
    - Chapter Articles and By-Laws, Alumni Directory, Rosters, Resume, Service Project List (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Chapter Family Tree, Sample Pedge Manual, Sample Pledge Quizzes, and Finals (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lambda Nu Chapter Record (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Officers' Reports - President and Service (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Officers' Reports - Fundraising, Membership, Social (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Officers' Reports - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Publicity (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Sample Service Record (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - Sample Service Record (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Slides (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Corresponding Committee/Administrative Materials, Fall 1995-Spring 1997 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Administrative Materials, Spring 1995-Spring 1996 (Box 2, Folder 33a)
  - APO Service, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fall 1996 Chapter History
    - Corresponding Materials
      - APO Alumni Mailing List (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Fourtieth Anniversary Survey Results (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Newsletters, Publications, Duke Alumni (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Membership History
      - General and Lists (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Slides (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - The Tome, Officer Statements, News Clips (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Minutes
      - Minutes, Fall 1995 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Spring 1996 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Fall 1996 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Pledge Materials (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Service Goals (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Service Sign-ups
      - Spring 1995 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
      - Fall 1995 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Fall 1996 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Administrative Materials, Fall 1996 (Box 2, Folder 49a)
  - National Convention Materials, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 49b)
  - Committee Notes, circa December 1996 (Box 2, Folder 49c)
  - Administrative Materials, Spring 1997 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - APO Service, Spring 1997 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Administrative Materials, Fall 1997 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Membership Materials, Fall 1997 (Box 3, Folder 52a-52b)
  - National Convention Materials, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 52c)
  - Administrative Materials, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 52d-52e)
  - National Convention Materials, 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 52f-52g)
  - Leadership Index, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Senior Banquet, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Slides, 1980-1997
  The slides document Lambda Nu volunteer and social activities. See folders 30, 31, and 38 for more slides.
  - 1980-1989 (Box 3)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
- Audio Recordings, 1998
  The Audio Recordings series contains one standard audio cassette tape.
  - Senior Banquet cassette tape, 1998 (Box 3)
- Composite Photographs, 1985-2002
  The Composite Photographs series contains oversize photographs of Lambda Nu members during a school year. The photographs include the names of the members as well as their positions in the group. They are arranged in chronological order.
  - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 4)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks, 1980-2003
  The Scrapbooks series contains scrapbooks made by Lambda Nu members to document their volunteer and social activities. They contain photographs, drawings, handwritten notes, typed documents, and other materials. Some scrapbooks have been interleaved with acid-free paper to protect their pages. The books are arranged in chronological order.
  - Fall 1980-Spring 1983 (Oversize-box 13)
  - Fall 1983-Spring 1984 (Oversize-box 41)
  - Fall 1984-Spring 1985 (Oversize-box 13)
  - Fall 1986 (Oversize-box 13)
  - Fall 1987 (Oversize-box 13)
  - Fall 1987-Spring 1988 (Oversize-box 8)
  - Fall 1988 (Oversize-box 8)
  - 1988-1989 (Oversize-box 8)
  - Fall 1989 (Oversize-box 8)
  - Fall 1989 (Oversize-box 9)
  - Fall 1990 (Oversize-box 13)
  - Spring 1991 (Oversize-box 9)
  - Fall 1991, 2 scrapbooks (Oversize-box 13)
  - Spring 1992 (Box 6)
  - Spring 1993, removed from original binding, pages placed in two folders (Oversize-box 14)
  - Fall 1993 (Oversize-box 14)
  - Spring 1994, removed from original binding, pages placed in a folder (Oversize-box 14)
  - Fall 1994 (2 scrapbooks) (Oversize-box 10)
  - 1995 (Oversize-box 10)
  - Fall 1995 (Oversize-box 14)
  - 1996 (Oversize-box 11)
  - Spring 1997 (Oversize-box 14)
  - Fall 1997 (Oversize-box 14)
  - Spring 1998 (Oversize-box 11)
  - Fall 1998 (Oversize-box 11)
  - Fall 1998 (Oversize-box 11)
  - 1999 (Oversize-box 11)
  - Spring 1999 (Oversize-box 12)
  - Fall 1999 (Oversize-box 12)
  - Spring 2001 (Oversize-box 12)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 7)
  - Undated (2 scrapbooks) (Box 7)
  - Undated (Oversize-box 12)
- Oversize Materials
  The Oversize Materials series contains oversize scrapbooks. The complete list of scrapbooks can be found in the previous series.
  - Scrapbooks
    - Fall 1987-Spring 1988 (Box 8)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Fall 1989 (Box 9)
    - Spring 1991 (Box 9)
    - Fall 1994 (2 scrapbooks) (Box 10)
    - 1996 (Box 11)
    - Spring 1998 (Box 11)
    - Fall 1998 (Box 11)
    - Spring 1999 (Box 12)
    - Fall 1999 (Box 12)
    - Spring 2001 (Box 12)
    - Undated (Box 12)
    - Fall 1980-Spring 1983 (Box 13)
    - Fall 1983-Spring 1984 (Box 13)
    - Fall 1984-Spring 1985 (Box 13)
    - Fall 1990 (Box 13)
    - Fall 1991, 2 scrapbooks (Box 13)
    - Spring 1993, removed from original binding, pages placed in two folders (Box 14)
    - Spring 1994, removed from original binding, pages placed in a folder (Box 14)
    - Fall 1995 (Box 14)
    - Spring 1997 (Box 14)